[music]
>> I'm going to talk about PyDancing Monty,
a project we have I mostly have been
working on since very late last year and
and a lot this year.
Uh, code execution is great for agents.
I think that is not particularly
controversial. The problem comes when
you actually need to go and use it or
build it. Most of the code or all of the
code execution solutions have have
trade-offs. So, Monty is our different
take. I don't claim that it will solve
everyone's problem all of the time,
but I think it is filling in a
a lacuna in the spectrum of different
options that that existed until now.
There are some other projects going on
in the same space, but but nothing quite
I think quite exactly the same as Monty.
So, inspiration for this, as I say, I
don't think
code mode is as um
uh, cloud flight call it or programmatic
tool calling as Anthropic have called it
is controversial anymore.
This is the idea that if you give an AI
access to write code instead of calling
tools directly, it can perform better,
it can be cheaper, it can be faster, it
can be more reliable, etc. etc. I think
that there is lots of nuance in how you
do that really well versus somewhat
well, which I will touch on here,
although I don't claim that we have
fixed fixed all of it.
Um, there is this continuum that I have
called here impotence versus chaos.
Um, when you harness an LLM, you make a
trade-off between control the control
you retain
and the capabilities you grant. At one
extreme, you have tool calling. The LLM
returns some JSON with a function name
and some JSON data, and you can tool
call one tool. Great, but it is somewhat
impotent in many cases because you have
this one very like simple way of
basically interacting with the outside
world.
The other extreme, you basically hand
over control of your computer to a
neural network. And the kicker is that
that neural network is trained by a
company who made their money out of
flouting all uh,
data conventions. So, we may not be
entirely keen to to do that all of the
time.
My point here is there are always
trade-offs. So,
if you look at this this diagram here,
and then it takes some some getting used
to, but but in terms of the continuum,
we have tool calling as I just just
talked about, Monty which I'm going to
get onto,
then you have the sandboxing services,
which are booming right now in the
middle, then you have coding agents uh,
in terms of furthest further along, and
then you have doesn't really happen that
much today, but at least theoretically
you have full uh, computer use. You just
hand over your computer to an LLM and it
can do everything.
In general, you substitute
uh, capabilities and power for control,
and you also increase the the
chance of failure, the uh, cost of
inference, the latency as as you move
across. Sandboxes are special in the
sense that they have a their own
separate price associated with them.
Um, but but my point is not to say that
one point on the spectrum is um,
is good or bad or that what some points
here are relevant and others aren't.
There are going to be people making
building economically valuable things
all over the spectrum. I just there
weren't many things between tool calling
and go and run the sandbox. And in
particular, that those those sandboxes
are problematic for people who are
individual builders or people with low
income, but they are also you have this
bathtub curve where you have individuals
have problems with it, and then
enterprises have massive problems
because if you are a bank or a
uh, yeah, financial institution, health
care institution, you can't just go and
sign up for the whatever startup is
doing tool call doing sandboxing and go.
I was also speaking to a big uh, or
getting in touch with a big car
manufacturer who want to run agents
inside their cars.
You even if you have a small LLM running
inside the car, yeah, sure, in theory
you can have some
VM like Docker, but it's not it's not by
any means trivial to set that up in the
the computer you have in a car. So, in
in those constrained situations where
you don't want to go and use an external
sandbox, that's where I think Monty will
will be most powerful.
So, what is Monty? It is a minimal
secure Python interpreter written in
Rust for running code written by AI
agents. In particular, this is not a
fork of I made a joke earlier that this
is a kind of slot fork of CPython, but I
said that's not true cuz it's not a
fork. Um,
it is uh, built entirely from scratch.
The only kind of foundational thing we
use is Astral or Ruff's AST parser.
Thank you very much. So, they have some
excellent code to go from pure Python
code the text to a structured data
object, which you can then use, and
that's obviously very fast, so we use
that, but from there on, the entire
implementation is written from scratch.
Uh, and the point is that because we're
writing it from scratch, nowhere in the
code base do we have an an open
implementation that can read a file.
Uh, and so
um, where we uh,
are building from scratch upwards rather
than taking an existing implementation
and chopping bits off until we think it
might be safe.
Um, this is a kind of hello world
example. We're going to
So, so obviously we then take Monty,
this implementation in Rust, and then we
wrap it with PyO3 to give you a way of
calling it from Python. What's nice is
because it's uh, purely a Rust
implementation, you can actually call it
similarly easily from JavaScript, and we
actually have other implementations in
uh, Dart and Kotlin um, in PRs. Uh,
Block in particular was super keen on
doing it in Kotlin, and then the day
after they submitted their PR, their
entire engineering team got uh, laid
off, so I don't think that one's going
anywhere, but um,
other ones might. So, I I go and run
this example. You can see it runs
instantly, and in this case just does
does a print, but we can do much more
powerful uh, things than that.
So, what is it?
Um,
The first point is um, that because
we're building it from scratch, we can
build it and nowhere in the code is
there even compiled in the option to
just simply open a file. The open
implementation or the
uh, socket implementation, they just
aren't there. So, we don't have to
reason about are we definitely sure
we've set the right compile time flags
or set this correctly, set up my C
groups. The code literally does not
exist in the code base to just go and
call open. Now, we do allow you to
simulate opening files, but that is all
via the system of callbacks. So, we
allow you to basically call um,
a prescribed list of functions on the
host. But we don't do that via the
traditional system of callbacks where
you pass a bunch of function pointers
into Monty, and it can then go and call
them.
Instead, we suspend execution whenever
you get to one of these external
function calls, and basically is very
much like tool calling. We return a
function name and the parameters to that
function.
Uh, sorry, the the arguments to that
function. The host then chooses whether
or not what what function to call,
whether or not to call it, what value to
return, and then execution continues.
The the kicker, and I'm kind of jumping
ahead here, the kicker of that
suspension of that um, returning from
execution
uh, is that we can snapshot the entire
runtime at that point if you want to,
and go [snorts] and put that in a
database and return later. So, if you
have a tool call that's going to take 2
hours or 2 days, you don't need your
Python process hanging around waiting
for that tool to finish. You just
snapshot your runtime, put it in a
database, and then when that tool
finishes, you resume. You could also
imagine that if individual users in a in
a SaaS application wanted to each have
their own
uh, context in which their agents write
code, you could be snapshotting each
individual user's code as they run it.
When they stop doing something, come
back tomorrow rather than having to have
one VM for each of your users.
The other thing I I I I lied. The other
thing we do take completely from Astral
is TY, their type checker. So, because
that's written in Rust, we're able to
build it into the binary, so you get
type checking completely built in
without having to to do any extra work.
Um, we can use this this callback system
for also allowing pseudo file system
access. So, we can basically do a
uh,
return a like read file and what that
file is called,
um, and the the host can decide how it's
going to deal with that. That also means
that if you want those files to list
live in object store somewhere, you can
completely do that. You don't need to
it's just as easy as implementing normal
files.
Because Monty is embedded, it runs in
the same process where um,
where you're running your agent, the
latency of um,
uh, starting it is around 1 microsecond.
I think in Python you generally get to
kind of 4 microseconds, but when you
compare that to you calling a sandbox
where you're taking around a second,
we're looking at like six orders of
magnitude of speed up.
Um, portability, as I said before,
because it's implemented in Rust, you
can run it anywhere. There's no worry
about which C groups do I need to be
able to go and control. Does it run on
Windows? Does it run on Linux? If you
can run Rust, you can run it.
Um, and yeah, no extra sandbox required.
But there is a trade-off, and I'm going
to be very blunt about this trade-off
trade-off.
Monty is a small subset of Python. It is
not designed to and it probably never
will be able to run your Python code.
This is not a situation where you can
say, "I've got my application, oh, can I
go and run it with Monty?" which was
always the
the hope with projects like uh, PyPy,
and honestly is the reason that there is
this graveyard of other Python
implementations was that to be a
alternative to CPython, you needed 99.5
nines of compatibility with CPython, and
even then if something went wrong, you'd
be like, "Oh, why don't we go back to
CPython?" This is not trying to be a
alternative to CPython. It is for a very
specific use.
Um,
so we have this very golden rule, which
is
Python is the truth.
We speak nothing but the truth, but we
are not claiming to speak the whole
truth. In other words,
if you want if you ask what is right,
what is right is what CPython does by
definition, but we are not claiming to
do all of the things CPython CPython can
do.
So, for example, I don't think I have it
in this deck, but at the moment you
can't define classes. I think we will
have classes. The standard library, we
have to implement each module in in Rust
effectively. So, we have like math and
re for regular expression and datetime I
think is coming soon. We'll have a
handful of the things that LLMs want to
use regularly. We are not ever going to
go and implement the full standard
library.
>> [snorts]
>> Um and there's a few other things like
context managers that I think will come
come over time.
Oh, and and most notably of all, you
can't use uh by default external
libraries. So, you can't install
Pydantic
um or requests. We will have workarounds
for those things. In fact, there's a PR
up now to implement most of NumPy um
and indeed he's also implemented most of
Pandas in that same PR,
which is the one of those like 10,000
plus PRs that we need to
collaborate with him to work out how to
um
how to how to get that solved. I side
story, I nearly went and closed that PR
and said, "What the hell are you doing?"
And then just before I did it, someone
in the team pointed out he's from a
large hedge fund who we're we're working
with closely. So, lucky lucky I didn't,
but shows the kind of people who are
interested.
Um
Yeah, so coming back to this to this
continuum and I think I touched on this
before.
The the conventional wisdom until now
has been start on the right and
basically constrain and constrain and
move towards the left when you need to
be when you need to be secure or when
you need to lower latency or when you
need to be able to have like restrict
what the LLM can do in ter in in the
interest of saving context. We start
from kind of as far left as we can and
then we add on individual bits. And the
point here is
we we know that there were lots of
things that are missing and we can have
people come along and report those bugs
and we can add them. But that is it's
it's like white listing. You start with
a restricted list and then you add
things when you need them starting with
a blacklist and going and playing
whack-a-mole with security issues. Not
saying we'll never have a security
issue, but like I think that the
foundational approach is better than the
like blacklist approach that is
ultimately what most sandboxing is
doing. I think the other thing to say is
you look at these other approaches
Docker was not designed to run untrusted
code. It was a designed as a way of
setting up a particular environment. Uh
it you know, it's a it is itself uh
15 different Linux tricks in a trench
coat. It is somewhat reliable, but it's
not perfect. Another one that people use
is Pyodide. Pyodide is an amazing
project for running Python in the
browser. It is a terrible way of
sandboxing both cuz it's slow and
because
uh it's often not that secure because it
wasn't designed for sandboxing. I'm a
massive fan of Pyodide. Hood is my
friend, but it's not designed for this,
which is why it doesn't work.
Um and that's true of most of the
low-level technology. Monty is the first
or one of the first projects where
someone's come along and said, "Let's
build something specifically for this
use case."
Um
So, I'm going to go into a demo.
This demo has failed quite a lot of
times
and so you you may see another failure
here, but I will I'll talk you through
it more than than running it
necessarily.
So, ultimately what we're doing here
we have some external functions, which
is what we're going to expose to the um
to the LLM. So, we give it this SQL
query interface where it gets to go and
query a particular SQL file.
Um it's going to use DuckDB internally.
And then we're going to have a plot
function, which is going to use
Matplotlib and generate a plot. The
point here is obviously inside the
runtime we don't have a plotting
library, we don't have a a SQL database,
but by exposing these functions into the
runtime, it can do arbitrary stuff on
the host and of course the kicker is you
pay microseconds of latency for calling
back to the host and no complexity,
whereas if you go and set this up with a
sandboxing service, being able to kind
of register functions from the host
within that sandbox is incredibly
incredibly complex.
Um so, yeah, we have plot and we have um
uh the show plot function and then we
have a display table, so it can display
a nice table to me that's going to go
and use I think rich internally to
display the table. I what I realize I
haven't got open here is the the context
of why I why I'm investigating this. So,
uh
the reason that I'm the the thing I'm
trying to understand is what the hell
happened here. So, this is the downloads
of Pydantic AI
and you can see that we had
a number of downloads we were quite
proud of like just shy of a million
downloads a day
um and then suddenly over the last few
days the number of downloads has shot
up. We were trying to work out why this
is. But I didn't particularly want to go
and spend my spend half an hour writing
SQL to investigate in BigQuery what what
was going on.
So, instead I exported all downloads of
uh Pydantic AI into a Parquet file from
from BigQuery. Then I just gave that
Parquet file to the model and said
investigate, work out what's wrong.
But of course it wants to also be able
to write code to to do these plots that
uses that data. So, just doing tool
calling would be either extremely slow
or not work.
And so, yeah, because we're going to do
um
type checking, we need to generate the
stubs for that external function
functions file. Some of this stuff will
soon be features of Pydantic AI, so you
won't have to do all of the setup. This
is a kind of from the ground up
implementation.
We have some prompt where we tell it
what it can and can't do in Python. At
some point lots of these you're not
allowed to use modules will be added.
Um we have our Pydantic AI agent, which
is ultimately what's going to going to
go and drive this. I will say
I don't know quite what they've done
with Opus 4.6 and Sonnet 4.6. The models
are great in general. They are woeful at
this kind of REPL coding. I think they
have been overtrained on some specific
form of code execution and so Opus 4.5
and Sonnet 4.5 do far better and I think
that's honestly a like tricky thing to
go and work out. If there are only going
to be certain models that can do this
it's going to be problematic. I suspect
long term they will all be able to.
So, we take our external functions that
we're going to be able to register.
We do this loop thing in Pydantic AI.
Again, you won't need to do that in
future.
Um but the real point is we we're not
even doing tool calling. We're just
telling the LLM
reply with some markdown which includes
some code blocks and we will go and run
that code for you and you can basically
include comments that you're going to
that will that will print out as we go
along. And here are the functions you
can call.
Uh and it's we're also going to insert
those stubs into the context so it has
functions it has access to.
And then we come down here to where we
actually run the code. I realized about
half an hour ago that our REPL
implementation that we're using here
doesn't yet have the type checking built
into it. That was an omission from me,
so that will get fixed. So, I'm like
currently doing Monty twice first just
to just to do the type checking. So,
this is all we need for type checking.
Type checking true and give it the stubs
that it needs to to enforce the types.
And then we're going to use this run
REPL async, which will take care of
extending extending the runtime as REPL
running it as REPL. One of the problems
we had with Monty to start with is these
models are built very much assuming that
they are going to be running a REPL
scenario is that everything they've done
before is going to be available and we
basically had to go and implement that
to make them to make them work better.
I'm running out of time, so I'm going to
cut going through all of this stuff, but
I'm very happy to talk about it later if
anyone has any questions
and run it and like I say, this
sometimes goes well and it sometimes
does a terrible job. So, it's a voyage
of discovery. Hopefully you can see see
my terminal.
I'll set that off. Won't be anything to
see because it'll be it'll be doing the
first like thinking about what to do.
But we can come over here into log fire
and we should be able to see pretty
quickly what it's doing.
So, you can see here from the um
I'm going to make this a little bit
bigger, but you can see the system
prompt that it got in full here.
Uh so, yeah. So, it had the description,
then it had the the stubs, then
ultimately was asked what to do.
And you see it returns some SQL to
describe the the table and you see it's
now able to generate these plots. And
again, this is happening in a scenario
where now most of us if we did this we
would just use Claude code and hope for
the best locally and that's fine. But if
you're doing something like this in the
cloud, you can't just run the Python on
that machine and hope for the best. And
so, this is this is kind of
I I would argue like a more powerful way
of doing
uh of doing that. You can see here there
was an exception. It got a typing error
from from TY that it was returned to the
model saying, "Here's the error of how
you got the types wrong." And you can
see it was then able to
uh fix that and the next time it ran
there was no error.
And you can see here it's still chunking
away working out what's going going on
and hopefully at some point it will get
to an answer and work out why the hell
someone started downloading our library.
Uh spoiler, it's definitely not real
usage. It's something weird that's going
on, but it's interesting.
Uh thank you very much. I might have
time for one question.
>> [applause]
>> One question. What LLMs?
Sorry? What's your preference for LLM?
Uh I have found
Sonnet Anthropic models to be much
better, but I as I say, 4.6 both Sonnet
and Opus
do some really weird things. I think
they have been like microtrained on a
particular code execution environment
and don't work very well. So, currently
both 4.5 models are are best.
Any other questions? Otherwise, we're at
time. Thank you so much.
>> [applause and music]